RAHUL TEVATIA

Cell: +1 (682) 283-6675 Email: rahul.tevatia@mavs.uta.edu
LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/rahul-tevatia-93660530/
Github: github.com/rtevatia4

Professional Summary

• Enthusiastic achiever with strong computer science background, project experiences and strong skillsets.

 Possess programming skills with over 4.5 years of professional IT experience in Software Engineering, Business Intelligence, Data Management, Data Visualization, Product Development, DevOps automation, system implementation and design.

• I am currently pursuing Master's in Computer Science to enhance my skills, knowledge and experiences.

Core Competencies and Skills

Programming & Scripting Languages: Python (proficient), Java (Intermediate), C (proficient), PL/SQL, JavaScript, **HTML+CSS**, XML, Shell Scripting (Batch).

Databases & Business Tools: Oracle Database, MySQL, SQL Server Management Studio, Data Visualization toolsets (i.e. Tableau, Visio), MS Excel (vlookup, index, pivot table, conditional formatting, chart and reports, trend analysis, VBA macros), SSIS/ETL, Eclipse, PyCharm, Visual Studio, JIRA, Git.

Operating Systems: UNIX, Mainframe Z/OS, Linux, Windows NT.

Other Skills: Data Integration (SSIS) & ETL, Data Modelling, System Infrastructure architecting and Design.

Education

The University of Texas at Arlington.

Master of Science in Computer Science, Specialization in AI and Databases.

Arlington, Texas, USA.

Aug 2019 - Anticipated 2021

Current GPA: 4.0

Dr. APJ Abdul Kalam Technical University (Formerly UPTU).

Bachelor of Technology – Computer Science & Engineering.

Gr. Noida, NCR, India. Aug 2010 - June 2014

GPA: 3.5

Professional Experience

Takaud Savings and Pensions B.S.C. (c)

Developer

Manama, Kingdom of Bahrain

Sep 2017 - July 2019

- Reduced **manual overhead** of operations and customer experience team by 60% by developing applications that provides the summarized daily transactions details of requested customers in graphical format.
- Created **visualization dashboards** for multiple financial reports to support various stakeholders' requests.
- Responsible for various developments, enhancements of the business solutions using **Python**, **Java**, **SQL**, **Shell Scripting and Data Visualization toolset**, majorly built many applications to support business functions and operations.

Cognizant Technology Solutions

Jr. Product Specialist

Kolkata, India

July 2014 - Aug 2017

- Migrated the many COBOL modules responsible for financial transactions to Java based frameworks.
- Increased the Oracle database and DB2 subsystem performance by 30% faster by optimizing the SQL queries.

Relevant Projects

OmniSearchAPP - Built the Takaud Client and Transaction Details lookup GUI utility to fetch requested client details and provides the summarized transaction activities. Used **tkinter**, **Pandas**, **pyodbc**, openpyxl python libraries and built visualization dashboards using **Tableau**.

Criminal Identification System - This was a web based project which aimed to help and support the investigative agencies in crime scene investigation and forensics. Used **HTML**, **CSS**, **Java**, **JSP**, Servlet, Java Script, MySQL.

Achievements and extra-curricular

- Received various organizational awards like "Pat on the Back", "Star Rookie of the Month" at Cognizant.
- "Project of the Year Clustered" Award in 2015 by TIAA, USA through Cognizant.
- Published a research paper at International Conference on Electrical, Electronics and Computer Science on, "E-Banking-A Revolution in banking sector Virtual Bank" Paper Id: ICEEECS-02024-232, Feb 2014, India.